{"tossups": [{"question": "While [emphasize] \u00a0living in this country, one revolutionary published an influential tome called The Development of the Monist View of History which got past the censors in his native country because it was filled with technical details. Another emigr\u00e9 fled from her native country to this country in 1881, and that emigr\u00e9 had earlier wounded Fyodor Trepov in an assassination attempt but was exonerated by the judge Anatoly Koni. Georgi Plekhanov and Vera Zasulich were part of a group that formed in this country, the Emancipation of Labour. An emigr\u00e9 who lived in this country attended the pacifist Kienthal conference. That emigr\u00e9, described as a (*) \u201cplague basilicus\u201d by Winston Churchill, travelled in 1917 from this country to St. Petersburg in a sealed train, and soon after published the April Theses. For 10 points, name this country, which was where Vladimir Lenin sought refuge from 1914 to 1917 in its cities of Bern and Zurich.\u00a0", "answer": "Switzerland", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The relatively progressive Hubert Murray spent 32 years governing a territory on this island and opposed the violence and hangings prevalent in its neighbour. The UN headquarters hosted negotiations for a treaty regarding sovereignty over this island in the New York Agreement. On this island, a controversial and likely-rigged referendum called the Act of Free Choice unanimously supported part of it becoming annexed to another country. A short-lived independent government on this island used the (*) Morning Star flag before ceding control to the UNTEA. During World War I, Allied forces captured the northeastern part of this island from the German Empire, which would become a League of Nations mandate governed by Australia. For 10 points, name this large island in Oceania, the site of a long-going insurgency against the Indonesian government in its west and a Commonwealth Republic in its east.", "answer": "New Guinea (accept Papua or Niu Gini)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "After a demonstration of this technology by sugar magnate Claus Spreckels, E.O. Hall & Son founded a company dedicated to it, whose employees would later form the HECO. The Iolani Palace was an early adopter of this technology after one of its chief advocates talked with King Kalakaua. An engineer named Harold P. Brown held public tests of this technology as part of his media campaign to oppose one variant of it. Visitors to the 1900 Paris World Fair like (*) Henry Adams were amazed by elaborate demonstrations of this technology called dynamos. George Westinghouse invented an alternative method of using this technology that was criticized for its use in executions and competed in public opinion with a direct form. For 10 points, identify this technology central to the war of the currents contested by Thomas Edison.", "answer": "electricity (accept answers involving electrical lighting, alternate current, direct current, lightbulbs or arc lighting)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A riddle by St. Aldhelm about this commodity claims that it contains \u201cno quality of any worth\u201d without the effects of its \u201cgleaming marrow\u201d. This commodity was the primary good traded by the K\u0101rim\u012b merchants in the medieval period in the Red Sea. The voyages of Zh\u00e8ng H\u00e9 coincided with a spike in the price of this commodity in Europe, which under the Y\u01d2ngl\u00e8 Emperor was being used to pay soldiers for their clothes. This commodity was the primary good traded for horses from the Middle East by the Vijayanagara Empire. It\u2019s not (*) ginger, but Duarte Barbosa wrote that the Nair caste was the primary producer of this commodity, which middlemen brought to the Portuguese at Cannanore on the Kerala coast. Contrary to popular belief, medieval Europeans likely did not use this commodity to make spoiled meat more palatable. For 10 points, identify this spice once coveted by Europeans, which is now paired on many tables with salt.", "answer": "black pepper (do not accept or prompt on other types of pepper)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One city on this body of water overtook Berezan Island in trade importance and produced dolphin-shaped coins. Strabo\u2019s Geographica claims that Leukon I, a ruler of a kingdom centered around this body of water, made a one-time donation of 2,100,000 medemni of food to Athens. As Greek settlement around this body of water increased, its name was changed from \u201cinhospitable\u201d to \u201chospitable\u201d. The city of Panticapaeum was the capital of a kingdom centered around a (*) \u201cCimmerian\u201d strait in this body of water. A group of Greek soldiers cried \u201cThalatta! Thalatta!\u201d upon reaching this body of water as reported by Xenophon. For 10 points, name this body of water, known to the Greeks as the Euxine Sea, that is connected to the Aegean via the Dardanelles and Bosporus Straits.", "answer": "Black Sea (accept the Sea of Azov or Lake Maeotis; accept the Euxine Sea before mentioned)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In the 19th century, Muslim residents of this modern country began to be all called \u201cMalay\u201d irrespective of their ancestry. The first Chinese immigration to this modern country happened during a visit by Herbert Hoover, then an officer for the CEMC, in 1904; those workers were all relocated back to China in 1910 after an election. Protestors in this modern country burned 1,200 registration cards issued by the government in front of the Hamida Mosque. Inspired by Trappist monks, an activist working in this modern country built the agricultural (*) Phoenix Settlement. In 1906, Asian immigrants in this modern country were subjected to an extension of the restrictive Pass Laws previously placed on its native population. An Indian activist working in this modern country became an ally of John Dube after he grew out of racist beliefs; that activist working in this modern country founded the Tolstoy Farm after a letter from the Russian writer advocating for non-violence. For 10 points, name this modern African country where Gandhi developed satyagraha while advocating for the rights of its Indian residents.", "answer": "Republic of South Africa", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Charles Stanish has hypothesized that a mile-long formation known as the \u201cBand of Holes\u201d was used by this empire to measure the tribute they received from the local people. This empire is estimated to have relocated 25-30% of its population, and at times attempted to recreate the specific pakarina spirits worshipped by the displaced community. Regional officials called apupanakas selected girls to be sent to the capital where the ruler of this empire could choose them to become (*) aclla (ahk-lyah). People traveling through this empire could stay at inns spaced a day\u2019s walk apart called tampus. Temporary movements of peoples were required by this empire to supply labor for the mit\u2019a system. For 10 points, name this empire, which brought peoples like the Chimor and Aymara under the rulership of Cuzco.", "answer": "Inca Empire (accept Tawantinsuyu)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Tradition holds that a brief republic was established between two ruling dynasties of this kingdom by a man named Evian, which ended after the people refused to accept Evian\u2019s son as their ruler upon his death. R.E. Bradbury proposed a \u201ccult of the hand\u201d in this kingdom, centering on an analysis of ikegobo, which were often placed on ancestral altars. A famous collection of the art of this kingdom includes a bust of Queen Idia. One account states that following Evian\u2019s death, the system under the previous ogiso kings was revived by inviting Prince Oranmiyan of Ile-Ife to rule this kingdom. After the final ruler of this kingdom stopped trading (*) palm oil with the British, an 1897 punitive expedition led by Henry Rawson toppled the kingdom and stole many of its famous bronze sculptures. For 10 points, name this long-lived kingdom in modern Nigeria, which names the present-day country to Nigeria\u2019s west.", "answer": "Kingdom of Benin", "category": "History"}, {"question": "People of this ethnicity were intimidated through taxation and prosperity confiscation to leave the Zone A and B areas that replaced the Morgan Line. During and after the Second World War, people of this ethnicity were killed in massacres named for the sinkholes, or foibes, their bodies were placed in. The Julian March was a geographic concept coined by a man of this ethnic group, which was later used to promote irredentism even in areas where they were not the majority. A writer of this ethnicity led a short-lived state called the Regency of (*) Carnaro that desired to be annexed by a nearby country, centered on the modern day city of Rijeka. After World War II, refugees of this ethnicity forced out of Istria became known as the esuli. A proto-facist state supported by people of this ethnic group was founded in the \u201cfree port\u201d of Fiume before it was annexed by a western neighbour. For 10 points, identify this ethnic group that were forced out of Dalmatia because of their connection to the Fascist state that occupied Yugoslavia.", "answer": "Istrian or Dalmatian Italians (accept answers involving Italians from Slavic countries)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A paper by Samson and Waller posits that the use of the \u201cbared-teeth motif\u201d on shamanic artifacts of this people was a display of benevolence, because if healing went wrong, the shaman could be castrated and clubbed to death. This people used, and provide the modern word for, an alloy of gold and copper called guan\u00edn. A group of this people initiated a rebellion after drowning, and for three days after, observing the corpse of, Diego Salcedo to prove that he was not divine. The chieftain Anacaona was hanged, and many of this people were burned alive, on the orders of (*) Nicol\u00e1s de Ovando. Magu\u00e1, Hig\u00fcey (ee-GWAY), and Jaragua (ha-RAH-gua) were among the domains ruled by caciques (kah-SEE-kayce) of this people on Hispaniola on Columbus\u2019 arrival in the Caribbean. For 10 points, what is this native people of the Greater Antilles?", "answer": "Ta\u00edno people (prompt on \u201cArawak\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \u201cCarib\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "While giving a speech in favor of this legislation, a Senator produced a wood fragment from George Washington\u2019s coffin. The tuberculosis-stricken architect of this legislation recuperated in Newport after this\u00a0 legislation initially failed to pass. During debate over this legislation, Henry Foote drew his pistol on Thomas Hart Benton. A Senator who supported this legislation declared that he wished to speak \u201cnot as a Massachusetts man, nor as a Northern man, but as an American\u201d in his (*) \u201cSeventh of March\u201d speech. The Wisconsin Supreme Court\u2019s decision to nullify this legislation was overturned in Abelman v. Booth. This legislation was brokered by Stephen Douglas and Henry Clay, and it included a controversial Fugitive Slave Act. For 10 points, name this legislation which admitted California as a Free State and which was passed 30 years after the Missouri Compromise.\u00a0", "answer": "The Compromise of 1850 (prompt on \u201cFugitive Slave Act\u201d before mention with, \u201cWhich was part of what larger piece of legislation?\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "William Henry Green criticized an attempt to calculate this quantity for assuming too much precision in its source material. The Omphalos hypothesis denies the validity of physical evidence for calculating this quantity. The ambiguity of the word yom is central to efforts to syncretize opposing views on the value of this quantity. Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte du Buffon, attempted to determine this quantity by measuring the cooling rate of a sphere of iron. Catastrophists countered (*) geological evidence for a relatively large value for this quantity by promoting the effects of one or more floods.\u00a0 In 1650, this quantity was calculated by James Ussher to be exactly 5,654 years based on genealogical evidence in the Bible. For 10 points, what is this quantity, now believed to be approximately 4.54 billion years, that represents how long the third planet from the Sun has existed?", "answer": "age of the Earth (accept logical equivalents, e.g. when the Earth was formed, date of Creation, etc.)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Only 184 out of 368,000 people voted against this movement in a referendum that referred to its goal as \u201calready completed\u201d. This movement gained support after the abolition of free-trade agreements called the \u201cInterstate Laws\u201d and the controversy over one parliament\u2019s inability to appoint its own consulates. Until delayed at the lenient Convention of Moss that preserved the constitution it created, this movement was briefly successful in 1814 during the power vacuum left by the Treaty of (*) Kiel. After initially opposing this movement by rejecting laws passed by the Storting, Oscar II accepted its success and renounced a throne shortly before dying. For 10 points, identify this movement that ended the rule of the Bernadotte dynasty in one country and saw Prince Carl take on the name Haakon VII as a new king.", "answer": "Norwegian independence (accept answers involving Norway breaking away from/breaking the Union with Sweden or Denmark)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "George Earl Church made two failed attempts to construct a railroad to facilitate the production of this commodity. This commodity was first commercially obtained by seringueiros. Henry Ridley created a sustainable method for acquiring this commodity, replacing the use of macadinho axes and allowing for industrial production. The Bar\u00e3o do Rio Branco negotiated the Treaty of Petr\u00f3polis to acquire the Acre region for producing this commodity. The growth of the city of (*) Iquitos as a center for the production of this commodity collapsed after the revelation of the abuse of the indigenous people of the Putumayo District by the Peruvian Amazon Company; that expos\u00e9, like one previously written about the Belgian Congo, was by Roger Casement. For 10 points, identify this commodity produced from the latex sap of a Brazilian tree.", "answer": "rubber", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A photograph taken in this state of an activist after he was shot three times won Jack R. Thornell a Pulitzer Prize for Photography. The Deacons for Defense and Justice provided security for an event in this state, while another participant flew to that event in this state after organizing the Open Housing Movement in Chicago. Demonstrators attempting to erect tents on the grounds of McNeal Elementary School were tear gassed by Canton police officers in this state. A speech given at Broad Street Park in this state\u2019s city of Greenwood introduced a term which was designed to supersede the \u201cFreedom Now!\u201d slogan of another organization. (*) Stokley Carmichael first publicized his idea of Black Power during that event in this state, to which public attention was brought by James Aubrey Norvell\u2019s wounding of James Meredith. For 10 points, name this state in which African American voter registration was promoted by the March Against Fear and the Freedom Summer.\u00a0", "answer": "Mississippi", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Along with brewing, a merchant of this industry nicknamed \u201cthe Wiseman\u201d turned dictator as a \u201ccaptain general\u201d was killed by an angry mob after forming an alliance against France. In the 12th century, immigrants from mainland started the English production of materials for this industry in Norfolk, and may have also brought the sport of cricket. Overseas trade routes that sent products of this industry from a group of cities called the (*) \u201cFour Members\u201d to Venice and Genoa led to the creation of a stock exchang called the Bourse. In the 14th century, sharp increases in English taxes on the export of raw materials needed for this industry, which was dominated by Flanders, forced producers to import a cheap Merino variety from Spain. For 10 points, identify this industry which imported plant-based materials from the Confederacy during the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "textiles (accept cloth; prompt on \u201cwool\u201d or \u201ccotton\u201d and ask \u201cWhat they were used to make?\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The propaganda film Sayon\u2019s Bell was created to show the \u201cheart-warming story of barbarians\u201d in its depiction of the title girl drowning in an attempt to help her Japanese teacher leave this region to fight abroad. A k\u014dminka policy enacted in this region was the \u201ctemple reorganization campaign\u201d, which sought to modify traditional religions to better foster Japanese patriotism. The Robin Hood-esque Li\u00e0o Ti\u0101nd\u012bng opposed early Japanese rule in this region until murdered by a compatriot. The Takasago Volunteers were recruited from indigenous peoples of this region, including (*) Attun Palalin, the last known Japanese WWII holdout. The end of the Japanese occupation of this region is celebrated yearly on \u201cRetrocession Day\u201d. For 10 points, identify this region, which four years after the defeat of Japan in WWII became the home of the Ku\u00f3m\u00ednt\u01ceng.", "answer": "Taiwan", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The papal bull Gravis admodum chastised people in this modern country for only practicing Christianity when they needed help against raids from the east. Several medieval relics, including a skull wrapped in Chinese damask, were found in a wall niche and the casket of Bishop Hemming in one of this country\u2019s oldest churches in the 1920\u2019s. An English bishop evangelizing in this modern country was apocryphally killed by a man named Lalli, who then stole the bishop\u2019s hat, which, after putting it on, removed his scalp when he took it off. A translation of the New Testament into a native language of this country was made in 1548 by (*) Mikael Agricola. An unsubstantiated crusade was launched against the peoples of this country by Bishop Henry and King Eric IX of Sweden, the original cult center of the former being Turku Cathedral. For 10 points, identify this country, whose medieval religious history saw them pulled between Swedish Catholicism and Russian Orthodoxy.", "answer": "Finland (accept Suomi)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A small state of these people names a zither made with 12 silk strings, which it exported along with high quality iron swords and helmets. A multi-ethnic kingdom known for purple porcelain ruled by these people may have collapsed in the 10th century after large drops in population caused by a difficult-to-date volcanic event sometimes called the \u201cMillenium Eruption\u201d. That state was shared with the semi-nomadic Mohe people during these people\u2019s (*) \u201cNorthern and Southern States\u201d period. The \u201cProtectorate-General to Pacify the East\u201d was established after the defeat of a king of these people. The Gaya Confederation was a small state sandwiched between two other Kingdoms ruled by these people during its own Three Kingdoms period, which ended with the invasion by the Tang dynasty that conquered the Bakje kingdom. For 10 points, identify this ethnicity, whose Three Kingdoms period included the Silla and Goguryeo.", "answer": "Koreans", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Historian Jeannette Sitte is best known for a book called \u201cA Short History of\u201d this region. The invasion of this region by Reman III led to the Four Score War, which ended with his assassination and the accession of Versidue. The two main groups living in this region formed the First Council and made peace after facing a Nordic invasion. During the Melethic era, the prophet Veloth led his people to settle in this region. A religion in this region venerates the Tribunal, a trio of gods named Sotha Sil, Almalexia, and (*) Vivec. While living in this region, the Chimer became the Dunmer, or Dark Elves, who would become a persecuted minority when they immigrated to nearby cities like Winterhold and Windhelm. For ten points, name this region of Cyrodil east of Skyrim, the title setting of the third game in the Elder Scrolls series.", "answer": "Morrowind", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}